Today's דף daf is ס"ד Samech Daled 64 and we pick up
on the bottom of ס"ג עמוד ב', Samech Gimmel Amud Bet,
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, five lines from the bottom. Let's pick up
there. 64? Wait. 63b is where we start, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
So we just spent a good two, three דפים dapim talking about
what are the characteristics of kosher birds and you know different types
of non-kosher birds that have different mixes of non-kosher characteristics and the
list in the תורה Torah and trying to identify what is on
the list of the תורה. Torah. And now we actually shift from
a lot of that sort of theoretical and admittedly
complicated conversation to a much more of a practical discussion. So let's
take a look. Today's going to be very practical. תנו רבנן, Tanu
Rabbanan, so our rabbis taught: לוקחין ביצים מן העובדי כוכבים בכל מקום.
Lokchin beitzim min ha'ovdei kochavim bechol makom.
You can purchase eggs from non-Jews wherever you are. ואין חוששין, V'ein
chosheshin, and you don't have to be concerned, לא משום נבילות, lo
mishum neveilot, that they came from birds that died, that were נבילות
neveilot and these eggs were found inside of them which would make
the egg a נבילה neveila as well. ולא משום טריפות, V'lo mishum
tereifot, or from birds that were that you know had some internal
injury and were טריפה tereifa and therefore the egg is also considered
something that comes from a טריפה tereifa and also not kosher because
those types of things are very unlikely. Of course 98-99% of the
eggs come from live birds which aren't טריפות tereifot so it's not
a problem. So now asks the גמרא: Gemara: ודילמא דעוף טמא נינהו?
Vedilma d'of tamei ninhu? Maybe they came from a non-kosher
bird? Total ignorance, you're not concerned that the bird is a טריפה
tereifa or a נבילה neveila but maybe it's a non-kosher bird. So
אמר אבוה דשמואל, Amar Avuha deShmuel, right, and something that comes from
a non-kosher animal is also non-kosher. So said the father of Shmuel:
באומר של עוף פלוני טהור, Beomer shel of ploni tahor, that the
merchant, right, the non-Jewish merchant is selling you, oh these eggs are
from are from chickens. They're chicken eggs. Now he didn't just say
they were chicken eggs. He didn't say של עוף טהור, shel of
tahor, but he said של עוף פלוני טהור. shel of ploni tahor.
That particular kosher bird. And רש"י Rashi says you have to say
that particular one because then you could go ahead and do a
comparison. If he just said oh these are from a kosher type
of a bird, then you'll say well doesn't look like anything like
chicken eggs to me. But if he says no no no these
are from chickens or these are from I don't know doves or
something like that then you'll go ahead and you can compare it.
And since you can compare it we are not afraid that he
will lie and misrepresent
with a with a known
sample of exactly that type of bird. Right. So I believe so
פלוני ploni does not have to mean that chicken over there. פלוני
ploni means a particular species, okay? And then if therefore he can
always be proven wrong, we can always do a test and therefore
he won't lie. Now this becomes an important example, an example of
an important principle which is when can you believe people in terms
of כשרות, kashrus, you know or things other things you have to
rely on them for halachic matters particularly when they might have a
vested interest. Okay, A it's a question about non-Jews who are not
normally part of our system and a question if we can normally
assume that they're believed in these matters
and especially also you know considering in general issues about hostilities between
Jews and non-Jews in earlier times and so on. So there's always
a suspicion in terms of that. And number two there's a vested
interest right because if you buy from him he's making a profit.
So sometimes the principle that's quoted or a concern is מסיח לפי
תומו. masiach lefi tumo. He just happens to be talking about it
to his innocence meaning he has no vested interest in it. He
just happens to be telling a story and it just so happens
in passing he mentioned something about oh yeah when I was going
to the chicken coop and blah blah blah. So something of that
nature is is one type of concern and this is not מסיח
לפי תומו. masiach lefi tumo. This is somebody that is very consciously
telling you where they come from and he knows that it's perhaps
relevant in your purchasing decision. So there you have a different issue.
There you have an issue about somebody not wanting to risk his
business. אומן לא מרע אומנותיה, Uman lo marei umnutei, a you know
an expert is not going to say something that is going to
undermine that is going to ruin his business if it turned out
that he has been misrepresenting himself. Now sometimes it has to do
more with an אומן uman means like an expert. So if like
I'm supposed to be an expert in birds and you ask me
a question or an expert chef and you ask me how something
tastes, if I give you a wrong answer it's going to show
that I'm not an אומן. uman. So you know that's a little
bit different. Here it's not so much about testing my expertise it's
just an issue about honesty. And maybe I'm just a passing through
salesman and after you buy from me today you're not going to
see me again. So there's these types of questions about which factors
are going to ensure that I'm telling the truth. So the important
one that's implicitly being stated here is not even אומן לא מרע
אומנותיה Uman lo marei umnutei but the question about
מילתא דעבידא לגלויי. milsa d'avida legluya. Something that will be revealed. If
it's very easy to check and to test and it's very it
will be very easy to say oh this guy's a liar so
in those types of cases we can more assume that I'm telling
the truth because it would be so easy to disprove me if
I weren't. So that seems to be the answer. He tells you
it's kosher and he tells you what type of kosher bird it
comes from. so that you could very easily test it. We will
see later if the גמרא Gemara adds other criteria in order to
believe him, but that's what we're saying now. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says ולימא של עוף טהור v'leima shel of tahor and here
it spells it out: what why can't he just say it comes
from a kosher bird? אי הכי איכא לאישתמוטי ee hachi ika l'ishtamutei
because then he could slip through, he could, you know, he could
get away. He could say, "Oh yeah, not chickens. I don't remember
what type of kosher bird but it was a kosher bird." And
then anything you ask him he'll have some excuse. But if he
tells you it's a particular type, then you'll be able to check
and to test. So the גמרא Gemara says ולבדוק בסימנין. v'livdok b'simanin.
Now why do you have to trust him? Why can't you just
check the way the eggs look? Now the סימנים simanim is not
all the סימנים simanim we were talking about before, the סימנים simanim
of the animal because you don't have the animal in front of
you. But now we're going to introduce a new concept that the
kosher eggs, eggs from a kosher bird and from a non-kosher bird
look different. So why don't we just check about those characteristics? What
are those characteristics? דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא. Beraita. כי
סימני ביצים כך סימני דגים. ke'simanei beitzim kach simanei dagim. The same
the same indicators for eggs are the indicators for fish. So the
גמרא Gemara says סימני דגים סלקא דעתך? simanei dagim salka dach? Do
you really think that it's the same indicators as fish? סנפיר וקשקשת
אמר
רחמנא. snapir v'kaskeset amar rachmana. The indicators of fish are fins and
scales. What, let's look for fins and scales on eggs? No. אלא
אימא כך סימני עוברי דגים.
ela
eima kach simanei ovrei dagim.
The same indicators for for eggs from birds are the indicators for
fish eggs. Okay, that the the same way to tell whether they
come from kosher fish you can tell whether they come from kosher
birds. What are they? The same types of things to look for.
ותניא גבי ביצים v'tanya gabi beitzim and here's what we taught by
eggs. Here's what to look for. אלו הן סימני ביצים. elu hen
simanei beitzim. These are the indicators for kosher eggs, from a bird
eggs.
כל שקודרת ואלגולגלת. kol shekoderet v'algulgelet. Anything that is spherical and round.
רש״י Rashi says, so both words רש״י Rashi says essentially mean the
same, but רש״י Rashi said if it had just said אלגולגלת algulgelet
round, it would have suggested in one dimen- in two dimensions, not
in three dimensions. It's actually interesting if you look at רש״י Rashi
what he says I might have thought it was. Is you said
if you look at the second line from the top, קודרת ואלגולגלת,
koderet v'algulgelet, חדא היא, chada hi, these are all really one thing.
דאי תנא אלגולגלת d'i tana algulgelet לחודה l'chuda it would imply עגולה
agula round כעדשה k'adasha like a lentil bean, which is you know
roundish actually it's more oval but it's also primarily in two dimensions,
and he says וכגבינה uch'gevina like cheese. So at first I read
this I said cheese? But then it occurred to me they used
to sell cheese in rounds, wheels, wheels of cheese, right. So right
there you go. Well in maybe fancy places, not where I shop.
In Italy, okay, it's a whole thick wheel.
Right exactly. So anyway, so the combination of these two means spherical,
okay, round in three dimensions. It's spherical but not totally spherical as
we know, eggs are a little more ellipsoid. So we'll get to
that in a minute. ראשה אחד כד, rosha echad kad, one end
of it is is like sort of is like a כד, kad,
like a pitcher, meaning it's sort of rounded, right, ovalish, וראשה אחד
חד v'rosha echad chad and one side of it is is sharp.
Okay, so it's egg-shaped, right? It's rounder at the top and point-
rounder at one end at the bottom and pointier at the top.
טהורה, tehora, then it's kosher. בין שניהם כדין, bein shneihem kadin, if
both ends
are oval-ish, rounded, או בין שניהם חדין o bein shneihem chadin or
both ends are pointed, come to more of a point, טמאין, tme'in,
then you know it's a non-kosher egg.
חלבון מבחוץ וחלמון מבפנים, chelbon mibachutz v'chelmon mibifnim, if the white is
on the outside and the yellow on the inside. The חלבון chelbon
and חלמון chelmon sound almost identical. The only way I remember the
difference is חלבון chelbon sounds like חלב chalav which is milk, so
it helps me remember that it's the white. Okay, so it's how
do you- what's the actual word for the white? The albumin, the
albumin. Okay, so if the albumin is on the outside and the
yolk is on the inside, טהורה, tehora, then it's kosher. Now do
you need that combined with the shape of the egg or is
that a separate indicator?
I think in general you open the egg, if the yolk is
on the outside and the albumin is on the inside, it's not
kosher.
It's from a non-kosher species. Okay, we're going to talk- say that
in a minute. But again it's not clear here is that in
addition to the egg shape or independent? Meaning are the- do you
need all of these criteria for it to be kosher or any
of them? So we'll see that in a minute. By the way,
that's only by now- by- by bird eggs. By, you know, by
fish eggs obviously there's no yolk and albumin so there it's all
about shape. Shape.
But the eggs of a chicken that haven't yet had been hatched
are only yolk. I mean I remember we used to have chicken
eggs that they were a delicacy. Yeah. They were they didn't emerge
from the chicken yet.
Oh oh they were in they were in the in the womb
of the chicken or
whatever in the-
right right, the white develops later. Yeah but this is after they're
laid. This is saying how do you test if it's from a
kosher bird or a non-kosher bird? Right so that's a good point.
I mean if you were selling an egg that you that- that
you couldn't test that didn't have yet white. Right that had been
laid. And then you wouldn't be able to test for this. That's
true. That's true.
But if it came from the chicken, you'd be okay.
Right, well, wait. It doesn't need this, right? This is not what
makes it... right, right. But what Dovie's saying is this is not
what makes it כשר. kosher. This is an indicator of what type
of species it came from. You know, if in particular a chicken
egg doesn't have these characteristics, if a particular chicken happened to lay
an egg that was pointed at both ends, it would still be
a chicken egg and כשר. kosher. Okay? These are just indicators of
what type of species it came from. You got a question, Robbie?
No. Okay. So, if it is however, חלמון מבחוץ וחלבון מבפנים, chelmon
mibachutz vechelbon mibifnim,
the yolk on the outside, the white on the inside, טמאה, teme'ah,
I don't know if that ever happens, טמאה, teme'ah, right, that's טמא.
tamei. חלמון וחלבון מעורבין זה בזה, chelmon vechelbon me'uravin zeh bezeh, if
the white and the yolk are intermingled, בידוע שהיא ביצת השרץ, beyadu'a
shehi beitzat hasheretz, השרץ, hasheretz,
you know that it is the egg of a rodent, like of
there are the שרצים shratzim in the תורה, Torah, the things that
are non-כשר kosher creepy things. We normally translate them as bugs, but
in the תורה Torah they're more like rodents, like moles and lizards
and chameleons and so on. Now, apparently, according to the footnote in
the Artscroll, because I wanted to, or alligator, so they said that
some, right, well, reptiles lay eggs,
right, so it said that their eggs basically have no white, they're
all yellow, so they're all yolk. So that might mean what it
means that they're mixed because even though they're all yolk, some of
what's normally the content of the white is part of the content
of the yolk. So that was an interesting suggestion that Artscroll made
that I checked because I did not know whether this was how
this correlated to our knowledge of these things, but it actually said
that there was no, there was no distinctive white in these things.
But it could be that mixed means it has some of the
elements of the white in the yolk. Okay, so these are the
indicators. So now that we're back to this, we're going back to
our question, which is: why do you need to trust the merchant?
Why don't you just look at these indicators? And then you could
know. So the גמרא Gemara says, לא צריכא דחתוכות. lo tzericha dechatuchot.
No,
he's selling actually chopped eggs. He's selling... he's not selling fresh eggs,
he's selling cooked and egg salad, cooked and chopped eggs, so you
have no way of looking at the egg shape. And so the
גמרא Gemara says, okay, וליבדוק בחלמון ובחלבון, velivdok bechelmon uvechelbon, why not
look at the white and the yolk? Presumably it's more like sliced
and chopped and you can see which is on the outside, which
is on the inside, and presumably that should suffice. So in this
הוה אמינא, hava amina, the question of the white and the yolk
is a sufficient indicator, not in addition to the shape of the
egg. So the גמרא Gemara says, בטרופות בקערה. betrufot beke'arah. No, he's
selling you basically scrambled eggs. Okay? So I don't know if he
cooked it or he's just selling you like you buy now
in the supermarket egg yolks, it's all like pre-mixed or for people
who only want egg white. So he's selling you pre-mixed eggs, you
can't look at the shape, you can't look at the white and
the yolk, and therefore you have to believe him. So the גמרא
Gemara says, וכי האי גוונא מי זבנינן מיניה? vechi hai gavna mi
zavninan minei? Can you even buy that from him even if he
claims that it's כשר? kosher? והתניא, vehatanya, we taught in a ברייתא,
braita, אין מוכרין ביצת טריפה לנכרי. ein mochrin beitzat tereifah lenochri. If
you have an egg that was from a chicken that was a
טריפה, tereifah, you can't eat it. Now you don't want to just
throw it out, cause it's a loss, so you sell it to
a non-Jew. However, there's a problem about selling it to a non-Jew.
He'll turn around and sell it to a Jew, and won't realize
that it's a טריפה. tereifah. So you can't sell it to a
non-Jew, אלא אם כן טרופה בקערה, ela im ken trufah beke'arah,
unless you actually mix it up and make it scrambled and sell
it to him that way. Because then you'll know that no Jew
will buy it from him, because a Jew looking at a scrambled
egg, again, not even cooked, but will know that there's nothing, no
indicators to check to make sure it's okay. So since a Jew
won't buy a scrambled egg, you can sell it to the non-Jew
and you're not afraid he'll turn around and sell it to the
Jew. ולפיכך אין לוקחין ממנו ביצים טרופות בקערה. ulefikach ein lokchin mimenu
beitzim trufot beke'arah. And therefore, either it's based on this or therefore
we said, you should not buy, you cannot buy scrambled eggs from
a non-Jew. So we're back to this question. You can't, if it
were already scrambled, you couldn't buy it from him even if he
claimed that it was כשר. kosher. If it's not scrambled, why do
you need to listen to what he says? Why don't you just
look at the indicators? Yes?
I think you said at the beginning, live birds are not טריפה...
treif... eggs from live birds are not טריפה. treif.
Eggs from כשר kosher live birds.
Oh, so כשר kosher meaning it's not a טריפה. treif.
It's of the כשר kosher species. An egg from an eagle's egg
is not כשר. kosher.
No, but this question here, like, the eggs from a טריפה... treif...
Yes, yes, eggs from a טריפה treif live bird are טריפה. treif.
If this chicken has a hole in its lung, right, then and
it's a טריפה, treif, then its eggs are also a derivative of
a טריפה. treif. Okay? So therefore, you can't eat it, but don't
sell it to a non-Jew unless you're sure that he won't turn
around and sell it to a Jew. Okay, so now you see
that if it has no indicators, it's mixed, you're not supposed to
buy it at all from נכרים, nochrim, because either because there's no
indicators to check or because we're afraid that he bought a טריפה
treif egg from a Jew and he only was able to buy
it because it was mixed. So then you can't be buying it
at all. And if it's not mixed, then why do you need
to listen to what he says? Why don't you just look at
the indicators? So the גמרא Gemara says, אלא אמר... ela amar... so
based on these questions, which are all really good questions, רבי זירא
Rabi Zeira said סימנים לאו דאורייתא, Simanim lav de'oraita, you cannot rely
on the indicators; those are not sufficient to make
a to rely on them for a biblically, meaning it's not like
the תורה Torah ever said, 'Here are the signs that you can
trust to determine whether it's a כשר kosher egg.' Now, לאו דאורייתא
lav de'oraita can mean one of two things. It could mean they're
not straight from the תורה, Torah, we figured them out ourselves. But
it means more than that because, for example, all of the indicators
of the bird of the birds, right? The long finger and the
bird of prey, etc., none of those are in the תורה. Torah.
We figured those out ourselves, but it was very clear from everything
we learned the last few days that those are a sufficient basis
to which to make a judgment call about whether a bird is
a כשר kosher bird or not, even though they're not in the
תורה, Torah, even though they're things that we figured out. So לאו
דאורייתא lav de'oraita means more than that. לאו דאורייתא lav de'oraita means
is that they're not a strong enough basis to make a decision
on a biblical matter for. Meaning what are the indicators of כשר
kosher and non-כשר kosher birds? That is sufficient. You remember the גמרא
Gemara even came up with its own indicators for mammals, like if
it had, you know, teeth on the top jaw, and all these
types of things that weren't in the תורה, Torah, but it felt
that these were absolute indicators and you can base a decision on
it. The thing for the eggs are not a hundred percent indicators
is really what it means, and therefore certainly for a biblical matter
you cannot base your decision on it. Now, this is actually a
borrowed phrase, because, well, of course one always says where did it
appear originally? But it seems that it originally appeared in the second
פרק perek of בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, where it talks about returning
lost objects. And the question is, it says you should keep it
in your home עד דרוש אחיך אותו ad derosh achicha oto until
your brother comes and searches it out and says, 'Hey, has anybody
found my lost object?' So the question is on what basis do
you trust the guy in returning it? And let's say he gives
certain indicators about it. Oh yes, it was green, and it was,
and it was this type of a thing, and I probably lost
it over there. So those are סימנים, simanim, those are indicators about
whether it was my object, you have to return it to me.
A major סוגיא sugya in the second פרק perek of בבא מציעא
Bava Metzia is סימנים דאורייתא או לאו דאורייתא. simanim de'oraita o lav
de'oraita. Are those really the biblical basis on which you return lost
objects or not? So it seems that this is a borrowed phrase
from there, but the point is, I mean obviously those you can
answer those questions differently, but the point is here these indicators are
not strong enough to make a decision on it just by these
indicators alone. And therefore you have to trust what the non-Jew says
as well, and the fact that what he says can be tested,
you have to trust that in combination with these indicators. And now
we're going to show how these indicators are לאו דאורייתא lav de'oraita
specifically about the eggs of birds, other cases like we said before
by other, you know, the very סימנים simanim of the birds themselves
are דאורייתא, de'oraita, are good for דאורייתא de'oraita purposes, but for the
eggs are not. ואי לא תימא הכי, Ve'ee lo teima hachi, if
you don't say that, הא דאמר רב אסי, ha de'amar Rav Assi,
what רב אסי Rav Assi said is שמונה ספיקות הן. shmoneh sfekos
hein. Remember we said yesterday that there were eight birds the rabbis
did not know whether or not they were כשר kosher or not
כשר kosher because whether their gizzard could really be peeled or not.
How do you define a peelable gizzard? So the rabbis didn't really
know if they were כשר kosher or non-כשר kosher birds. So the
גמרא Gemara says, 'I have a great way to determine whether any
bird is a כשר kosher bird or non-כשר kosher bird. What's the
way? לבדוק בביצים דידהו, Livdok bebeitzi didhu, check the eggs!' Right? Oh
my god! If these things is a really way to determine כשר
kosher and non-כשר kosher eggs, then it's also a way to determine
כשר kosher and non-כשר kosher birds. So I can solve all my
problems, just check the eggs. Now maybe he would have said at
the end also what's really round at the bottom, what's really sharp
at the bottom, maybe there's some ambiguity there as well, but the
גמרא Gemara assumes not. Why not just check the eggs? אלא שמע
מינה סימנים לאו דאורייתא. Ella shema mina simanim lav de'oraita. You see
that these indicators for the what's כשר kosher and non-כשר kosher eggs
are not a hundred percent and cannot be relied on for biblical
purposes and you have to combine it with the statement of the
seller and with the fact that his statement can be tested. אלא
למאי הלכתא תני לה? Ella lemai hilchta tani lah? So then why
therefore are we telling us what these indicators are if you can't
rely on them? הכי קאמר, Hachi ka'amar, because here's what it's saying:
ביצה ששני ראשיה כדין, beitzah sheshnei rasheha kadin, if both of the
ends of the egg are rounded, או ששני ראשיה חדין, o sheshnei
rasheha chadin, or they're both pointed,
או חלמון מבחוץ וחלבון מבפנים, o chelmon mibachutz vechelbon mibifnim, or the
yolk is on the outside and not the white, then ודאי טמאה.
vadai tmeiah. If it has any of the negative indicators, it's certainly
not כשר. kosher. And therefore no matter what anybody tells you, he
could swear from here till tomorrow that it's כשר, kosher, if it
has any of the negative indicators it's definitely not כשר, kosher, which
is if it's not round at one end and pointed at the
other, and if it's not the yellow inside, you need both of
those to be correct. Only then is it possible that it's כשר,
kosher, but if you don't have either if either of those are
missing, the shape or the yellow and white, then he's certainly lying,
it's certainly not כשר, kosher, you can't buy it regardless.
And if it's not certified by OU...
there you go, that's what's missing from the גמרא. Gemara. Now,
ראשי חד חד, ראשי חד כד, rashei chad chad, rashei chad kad,
it's a little bit hard to follow the חד chad can mean
one, it can mean sharp, if one head is sharp and one
head is
round, וחלמון מבפנים וחלבון מבחוץ, vechelmon mibifnim vechelbon mibachutz, and the white
is on the outside and the yellow's on the inside, so it
does all the right indicators, then it's possible it's כשר *kosher* and
then it depends on what he says. ואמר לך של פלוני וטהור
הוא *veamar lach shelo ploni vatahor hu*, if it's a chicken for
a chicken's egg and it's כשר *kosher* chicken's egg, סמוך עליהם *smech
aleihem*, then you can rely because then you also have his claim
and it's a claim that can be somewhat tested by doing a
comparison. בסתמא *bistama*, if he didn't make that claim, he just said
it's a כשר *kosher* egg, or didn't say it's from that even
a chicken's egg, or he didn't say anything, then לא תסמוך עליהם
*lo tismoch aleihem*, do not rely on them. Now, why not? First
of, besides it has all the כשר *kosher* indicators, why wouldn't I
go ahead and even if he doesn't say it's a chicken's egg,
let me compare it to chicken's eggs, let me maybe see, let
me compare it to other eggs? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
no, because this, this is why you can't rely on the סימנים
simanim. *simanim*, דאיכא דעורבא דדמי לדיונה *deika de'urva dedami leyona*, there are
raven eggs that are similar to dove eggs. Now again, apparently because
I don't know any of this, so I checked the footnotes in
the ArtScroll and they claim that the shape of the two actually
is similar, that raven eggs actually do, this is what the ArtScroll
claims, I don't know where they're getting their facts from, but anyway,
you do have this like, you know, rounded at one end and
pointed at the top. However, it does say that, you know, in
the vast majority of times they're not similar because they're a different
color than the than them, but at least the shape, you know,
we haven't been mentioning color, at least the shape is similar. So
that's why it is not a definite proof, the shape and the
yellow and the white, and that's why if the non-Jew does not
make a specific claim, we can't just, you know, on our, you
know, we can't just make certain assumptions on our own because maybe
this actually is a non-כשר *kosher* bird, maybe there are other non-כשר
*kosher* birds besides just the raven and the, you know, and the
and the dove, and that actually their eggs do look similar to
כשר *kosher*. So it's the combination of the two, that all the
indicators are correct and he's making a claim which to some degree
can be tested, that allows us to go ahead and to rely
on it. Now, yes, you had a question?
No, you just search everything in the marketplace in their
in the time of the ראשונים Rishonim *Rishonim*, that's an excellent question,
I'm going to tell you, I'm going to get to that in
a second, okay? Because I want to talk about the practical, let
me first talk about a theoretical point here which is the question
about so when can you trust somebody who's making a claim, right?
And a claim that can be tested. Here it seems like you
need it to be backed up by all of this evidence, right?
If it wasn't backed up by this right evidence in front of
you, somebody just says something, even if there's a way to test
for it, maybe you can't trust them. So right, because we started
by saying somebody says something, it can be tested for, so you
can trust them. Here we're saying it needs to be corroborated by
all of this evidence. So it's possible, so that gets into these
regular questions, right, about when can you trust people and under what
circumstances and are they going to hurt their business and is it
something that עבידי לגלוי *aviday l'gilluy* and all these types of questions.
So it's possible that one reason that this is needs corroborating evidence
is exact is because the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* was already indicated that
sometimes you can't, you know, certain eggs look like other eggs. So
if like a raven egg looks like a pigeon egg, you know,
maybe a chicken egg looks like another non-כשר *kosher*, I'm the גמרא
Gemara's *Gemara*'s not saying this, I'm just saying it's a possible way
of reading what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s getting at, you know, that
maybe even the to prove it or to disprove it is not
a hundred percent. So that's might be why you need a collective,
you need the corroborating evidence and the claim. The corroborating evidence on
its own doesn't do it because there are some eggs that are
similar to כשר *kosher* eggs and therefore also maybe his claim alone
doesn't do it because there are some eggs that are similar that
aren't really כשר *kosher*. But maybe the combination of the two, that
could be a way of explaining, you know, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
explained why you needed his statement, I'm sort of saying the reverse,
why isn't his statement sufficient? And it could be the same issue,
but leads to important questions about under what circumstances and with what
type can you rely on the, you know, statements and the claims
of facts of non-Jews to make halachic decisions based on it. Some
people take a more hardline position based on this גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*
and say that even when there is concern that even when it's
a circumstance that you can, you know, disprove a person and it
would be easy to disprove them and so on, you know, maybe
this גמרא Gemara's *Gemara* for us tells us that you you can
never just rely on the statement, you always need corroborating evidence. That's
not clear, you know, why you needed the corroborating evidence here, but
that's one question about how about about those claims. Now what I
want to talk about now is a minute is two important practical
issues, two very practical issues that תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* raises, which is
how in the before the OU, how people would make purchasing decisions.
Now so first before we get to the eggs of of birds,
let's talk for a minute about the eggs of fish. So we
all know that there's, right, the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says why not
use these indicators to prove whether it's a כשר *kosher* or non-כשר
*kosher* bird as well, they're not a hundred percent. So you could
have also asked the question about why don't you use the indicators
to prove כשר *kosher* or non-כשר *kosher* of fish? You'd say who
needs it, you can just look at fish, fins and scales. But
as we know from recent debates about swordfish and sturgeon and so
on, sturgeon is not the same as swordfish, is it? No, okay.
Anyway, that it's not always clear what constitutes the scales. Some say,
well, I always thought the issue with the swordfish was that they
shed their scales when they came out of water. Apparently that's not
the issue. The issue is is that with some fish the issue
is the question is about... what happens if they have their scales
when they're young and not older, but I think with the swordfish
and the sturgeon, what I was able to look into last night
was that the גמרא Gemara also talks about the scales being sort
of not like armor but more like, you know, more instead of
like hardly connected on, but more like peelable off. So what and
the issue apparently with the swordfish is that when you try to
if you peel try to peel off the scales, some of the
flesh comes with it. They don't peel off easily. Now it's about
now apparently this was Moshe Tendler's ruling from about I don't know
40 years ago. Apparently for about like 200 years Jews in Europe
and even in the US have been eating swordfish, right? But then
they said, well, look, you know, it doesn't really peel off, da-da-da-da-da.
So anyway, so the question
is, is what by the way you know those two guys that
are always trying to rewrite Ari Greenspan and Ari Zivotofsky, right? So
they're always having these like things about trying to eat kosher animals
that are not normally eaten to reinforce the מסורה. mesora. So at
one of their at one of their meals they actually had swordfish
available and had big booklets available for people to look at all
of the discussions and were encouraging people to make decisions for themselves
whether or not they're kosher and to eat it or not. Let
me just finish the point. So in that context, so the question
is, well how about checking the eggs? So תוספות Tosafot says, well,
or do we say no the גמרא Gemara says you can't rely
on these סימנים. simanim So based on a certain גמרא Gemara in
a certain discussion elsewhere about the eggs of fish, תוספות Tosafot says
maybe you only can't rely on the סימנים simanim by bird eggs
because it says you have the raven's eggs that are similar to
the dove's, but maybe you can rely on the סימנים simanim by
fish eggs and based on that determine what type of species are
kosher or not. So if you take a look at this תוספות
סימנים לאו דאורייתא, Tosafot simanim lav de'Oraita, תוספות Tosafot says like this,
he says, he says ועל
זה אנו סומכים, ve'al zeh anu somchim, it's about 12 lines down,
first word on the line is ועל זה, ve'al zeh, or maybe
15 lines down in the תוספות סימנים. Tosafot simanim. He says ועל
זה אנו סומכים ve'al zeh anu somchim to eat those fish that
they call ברבתא barbta בלאז. be'laaz. I have no idea what it
was. I tried to figure it out, but you know, try typing
in an old French word in Google without even knowing how the
vowels work. But anyway, it's that we eat that ואפילו ידעינן דנשרו
הקשקשים בשעה שעולין מן הים, ve'afillu yad'inan de'nashru ha-kaskasim be'sha'ah she-olin min
ha-yam, and apparently they had no visible scales when they were taken
from the sea. So the question was, well maybe they shed their
scales when they came out of the water. He says even if
we don't know if they shed their scales, he says בשעה שעולין
מן הים סמכינן אסימני וברי דגים, be'sha'ah she-olin min ha-yam somchinan a-simanei
u-barei dagim, we rely on the indicators by the eggs to determine
that this is a kosher species of fish. So that's quite fascinating.
Here there was a practice to eat a fish which did not
have visible scales. He tried to figure out how we do that
and said maybe it's on the basis about the eggs, but then
he goes on to say from the ירושלמי Yerushalmi it sounds like
you can't rely on the סימנים simanim? of the eggs and he
never gets back to figure out how come we eat this fish.
So that's one question about already something like this. Is it really
count as scales? Does it really have scales? Can we use the
eggs? Then he's going to get to talk about about bird eggs
in a minute. Bobby, you have a question?
I just thought it was very interesting how nature things happen later
on in time. It was a ruling, a rabbinical ruling that we
don't eat swordfish, okay. I don't know if anybody follows the latest
literature on fish. One of the most poisonous fish in the water
is swordfish. Really? It holds much more mercury. I mean Consumer Reports
10 years ago did this whole thing about what fish to avoid,
and restaurants love to serve it because it's a lovely gorgeous fish
and it's like a steak inside of it, but it is a
poison kind of fish. So it's like השם Hashem is protecting
us even
when we're trying to, you know. There you go.
There you go. Okay.
Let's then move on with what
we were...
very nice. ישר כח. Yasher koach.
So
why
is it סימנים? simanim Why is it not just the fish eggs?
Do you know of just the shape?
Just the
shape of the eggs?
No yellow and white, right? All right.
So that's one thing, right, just repeats.
And there by the way one more thing please just.
Yeah, go ahead.
There are loads and loads of issues of problems, health problems of
eating farmed fish. So that's a whole other. Okay.
So Seth just reminds us that the yellow and white is and
what I said before, the yolk and the white is only an
issue by bird eggs. By fish eggs it's just about the issue
of shape. Just about that it should be rounded at one end
and pointed at the other. So I don't know, when I buy
salmon caviar and these other fish eggs, yeah, they all look totally
spherical, don't they?
Spherical, no?
When you get it
like at a wedding, yeah, right.
Yeah, I know they look totally spherical.
It's like a cluster.
Yeah,
so I don't know,
he says that.
Right, I don't know. So let's go on. That's one thing. The
other thing is about the about the about the bird eggs. So
now we've got a... so they've got a... So okay so for
the ראשונים to go ahead and to buy eggs that were being
sold by the non-Jewish farmers fine. So you go ahead and you
look at it and they say they're chicken eggs and they look
right, you know, שלום על ישראל. Shalom Al Yisrael. But the question
was
that
they didn't just buy eggs, they also bought products that had eggs,
and in particular they bought bread that was made with eggs. So
now we've got a question, right, that can't be—how's that any better
than the ביצים טרופות? beitzim trufot? Right? So you can't look at
the white and the yellow and the shape and all of these
types of things. So this actually is—and this—I want to read you
a line or two from תוספות Tosafot because it's a good indicator
about exactly this, about how they used to live and make decisions
in a world before הכשרים, hechsherim, and how like this type of
thing would never occur to us nowadays, the types of decisions they
make, but it really talks to you about how you can make
decisions, you know, when you don't have a הכשר hechsher industry out
there to be making them for you. So תוספות Tosafot says like
this, I'm sorry, what?
Or than North America, right.
He says like this. He says the last line of the narrow—of
the middle-sized lines, first word of the line, first line, first beginning
of the line: ומה שאנו לוקחים מעובדי כוכבים ביצים אף על פי
שאינם אומרים של פלוני טהור הם. u-mah she-anu lokhim me-ovdei kokhavim beitzim
af al pi she-einam omrim shel ploni tahor hem. So he says,
how about the first question, which is we buy their eggs and
we don't test them to say, oh, what type of eggs are
they? They go around, they sell their eggs, we never make a
point of saying, you know, where they come from, which types of
eggs are they? So he says: אנו סומכים על רוב ביצים שמצויים
בינינו דשל עופות טהורים הם. anu somkhim al rov beitzim she-metzuyim beineinu
de-shel ofot tehorim hem. So just like that, he gets rid of
the גמרא's Gemara need for the non-Jew to make a claim. He
says, for us, where are you going to get other than chicken
eggs or other than kosher eggs? You know, 99% of the eggs
out there. Sort of like, you know, the whole discussion about חלב
ישראל. chalav Yisrael. Do you have to worry about non-kosher milk if
the only milk around is kosher milk? So תוספות Tosafot just like
that says, you know, we don't worry about the non-Jew corroborating, even
though how hard would that be to ask him what types of
eggs they are, but we don't bother because of course that's not
a concern for us that they came from non-kosher eggs. ומה שאנו
לוקחים מן העובדי כוכבים אובליאש
וקנטיאש—I u-mah she-anu lokhim min ha-ovdei kokhavim oblias ve-kantias have no idea
but these were various types of pastries and breads that had eggs
in them—שנילושו בביצים, she-niloshu be-veitzim, אף אגב דאסירים הכא ליקח מהם ביצים
טרופות—although af agav de-asirim hacha likach me-hem beitzim trufot here you cannot
take from them, you know, eggs that are already sort of scrambled—בקערה,
be-ke'arah, לא דמיא דהכא איכא ריעותא מדזבין להו עובדי כוכבים טרופות
בקערה. lo damya de-hacha ika re'uta mi-de-zavin le-hu ovdei kokhavim trufot be-ke'arah.
Here, the fact that he wouldn't sell it to you whole and
is only selling it to you mixed raises doubts and suspicions. שמע
מינה דמוכח מילתא דמשום הכי מוכרן לפי שהן טריפה או טריפה, she-ma
mina de-mukhach milta de-mishum hachi mokhran le-fi she-hen tereifah o tereifah, פת
שנילושו בביצים, pat she-niloshu be-veitzim, but if you're just buying a normal
recipe that has in it eggs and it's got, you know, dough
and eggs, לא חיישינן ואזלינן בתר רוב ביצים שאינם טרופות ולא חיישינן.
lo chashinan ve-azlinan batar rov beitzim she-einam trufot ve-lo chashinan.
Now, we assume what likelihood is it that it's—it's probably kosher eggs,
all you have around here are from kosher birds, and then number
two, it's probably not from a bird that's a טריפה. treifah. What's
the likelihood of that? So just making straight assumptions based on, you
know, percentages and likelihood, even though the גמרא Gemara specifically says you
need the non-Jew to say this and you don't buy it if
the egg is already cracked. Yeah, but תוספות Tosafot. says for us
there's no reasonable things to be concerned about, so we go ahead.
And there's one last thing. How about ולא חיישינן שמא היה בהם
דם? ve-lo chashinan shema haya ba-hem dam? Maybe there were blood spots.
דרוב ביצים אין בהם דם—that de-rov beitzim ein ba-hem dam most eggs
don't have
blood spots. Okay, etc., etc. And he then goes on and then
his last question is about בשל עכו"ם bishul akum and פת עכו"ם
pat akum and so on. But this is a great example of
how they would make decisions when you didn't have the ability to
actually, you know, check every single detail. But what's actually fascinating is
some of these things they could have at least asked. They could
have said, oh, where do the eggs come from? But it was
just wasn't the practice to ask. Everybody was assuming, you know, everybody
knew they were chicken eggs and was working with that assumption. So,
you know, it's quite interesting how you would operate in a context
where you did not have a הכשר hechsher industry. Interesting question.
So, you know, is to what extent is this to try to
determine reality and to what extent is this trying to justify the
common practice?
Right. Well, that's clear in both all of these cases of תוספות.
Tosafot He starts with the fact that this is the practice, how
do we come to—how do we explain it?
Right. Same thing recently with milk, right? For cows.
So what if it changes and—and that it turns out that most
chickens, you know, have lung disease, right? Right.
Well, well, that's true. Meaning—oh, I thought you were saying something else.
Meaning תוספות Tosafot is not proactively saying, oh, I know everybody is
concerned about buying these pastries, but don't worry because we can just
make these assumptions. Meaning תוספות Tosafot is starting from the fact that
this was the accepted practice and he's trying to justify it. That's
what I thought you were saying, which is also true, which is—yes,
you know, is
that same thing with milk?
Right. Everybody drinks milk. Right. Yes. So I assume that if those
realities were to change and תוספות Tosafot could not sort of, you
know, make a claim like of course the majority are okay, that
he might—that he would have to. But of course his inclination always
is to defend the practice if at all possible, you know. But
yeah. All right.
Imagine if you were buying scrambled eggs and you asked to check
and see the eggs they were from. Would that be...?
Ah, that's an interesting question. I, you know, assuming
that, well, depends also because the way תוספות Tosafot frames it and
what's implied in the גמרא Gemara is We might have to be
concerned that the reason they're scrambled is because they were טריפה. treif.
They were from a טריפה treif chicken and bought some, so it
doesn't matter if you could check the egg. The fact that they're
scrambled raises concerns that he was, you know, that he brought it,
right?
Like I went to his kitchen and
bought—Well, in the context of the גמרא, Gemara you know, where there's
a basis for concern that it's a טריפה, treif, or he went
out of his way to scramble it, as תוספות Tosafot points out,
when you don't—those do not raise doubts, the fact that they're mixed,
there's a reason that they're mixed, right? So, you know, like in
his case about the pastries or whatever, תוספות Tosafot said it wasn't
a concern. So תוספות Tosafot is willing to reassess and to actually
do away with some of the גמרא's Gemara criteria based on, you
know, what type of concerns really are present. Okay, so let's get
back to the גמרא. Gemara
Okay. So אמר מר, Amar Mar, so now we've said
חלבון וחלמון מעורבין זה בזה, chelbon ve-chelmon me'uravin zeh be-zeh, the white
and the yellow are mixed, בידוע שהיא ביצת השרץ. yedu'a she-hi beitzat
ha-sheretz. You know that it is the egg of a שרץ, sheretz,
which we'll say means some type of a reptile. So the גמרא
Gemara says למאי הלכתא? lema'i hilchata? So why do I care? אמר
רב עוקבא בר חמא, Amar Rav Ukva bar Chama, I mean, who
cares if it's of a reptile or if it's of a non-kosher
bird? Either way, it's not kosher. So אמר רב עוקבא בר חמא,
Amar Rav Ukva bar Chama, לומר שרקמה ונקבה, lomar she-rikmama ve-nikva, if
the egg, they already started—רקמה rikma means like it already started to
fertilize—inside of it the, you know, the baby lizard or whatever the,
whatever the baby is, the baby started to form and there's a
hole in the shell of the egg, then מטמא כעדשה, metameh ke-adashah,
it causes טומאה tumah even the size of a lentil bean. Because
although if you were to actually touch, if you touch an egg
it doesn't cause טומאה, tumah, but the actual, an actual lizard does.
An embryonic lizard can also cause טומאה tumah that's growing in the
egg. But you have to be able to touch it. Now if
there's no hole in the shell, then it's not touchable. If there
is a hole in the shell and it's in theory touchable, then
it's considered as if you touched it even if you only touched
the shell because the shell is a protector of it. So touching
the shell and the protector of something is like touching the thing
itself, but only if the thing itself is touchable. That's why there
needs to be a hole in the egg. So if there's a
hole in the egg and it has begun to form the embryo,
then it can cause טומאה. tumah. And that's why it matters that
it is a non-kosher, that it is a non-kosher lizard or שרץ
sheretz as opposed to a non-kosher bird, because a non-kosher lizard causes
טומאה tumah even the size of a lentil bean, whereas a non-kosher
bird might not cause any טומאה, tumah, but if it does cause
טומאה tumah it's certainly bigger than the size of a lentil bean.
So that's why it's relevant to know that this is the, a
lizard egg. So מתקיף לה רבינא, matkif lah Ravina, רבינא Ravina asks
on this, דילמא דנחש היא? dilema de-nachash hi? One minute, there are
other reptiles that don't cause טומאה, tumah, meaning the תורה Torah only
lists eight שרצים sheratzim that cause טומאה. tumah. Okay, some of them
are actually small rodents, mammals or whatever, some of them are like
lizards and so on, and it only lists eight. They're all non-kosher
to eat, but only eight of them actually cause טומאה. tumah. So
just to tell me, "Hey, this is a, you know, a lizard
egg or a reptile egg," I can't use that as a basis
for making a decision about טומאה tumah because I don't know what
reptile, and maybe it's a reptile like a snake that doesn't cause
טומאה. tumah. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא אמר רבא שרקמה ואכלה
לוקה עליה משום שרץ השורץ על הארץ. ella amar Rava she-rikma ve-achlah
loka leh mishum sheretz ha-shoretz al ha-aretz. You're right. Forget about טומאה.
tumah. Back to forbidden foods. If an embryo started to develop and
you ate this egg, then you would have transgressed the prohibition of
eating a, of eating a, you know, a creepy thing, which basically
includes rodents and lizards and all those non-kosher creepy things. Now why
is it important that it's a, that we know it's a reptile
egg? Because it's true, if it were a bird egg and a
non-kosher bird, you would also transgress for eating the bird, of eating
the egg of an eagle, which is a non-kosher bird. But if
you want to know which transgression you've done, or if we want
to give you lashes so we want to have, give you the
right type of a warning, so it's important to know you didn't
do the transgression of eating a non-kosher bird, you did the transgression
of eating a שרץ, sheretz, of eating a creepy-crawly thing. Okay, so
it's a different transgression. Now the other important question to ask here
is: why do I care that the animal has begun to form?
Rabbi Eleazar, haven't you been telling us for a long time that
anything that comes from a non-kosher animal is not kosher, right? Haven't
we just been learning that eggs from non-kosher birds are not kosher?
So even if the lizard and the embryo hasn't formed, if it's
a reptile egg, it's not kosher because it derives from a non-kosher
animal. So the simple answer to this, which the רמב"ן Ramban says,
is yes, but it's not the same prohibition. Meaning the תורה Torah
says, you know, don't eat non-kosher animals. The rabbis learn out that
there's also a prohibition to eat things that derive from non-kosher animals,
but it is not the same prohibition. If I drink milk from
a camel, I have not transgressed the prohibition of eating a camel.
If I eat eggs from an eagle, I haven't transgressed the prohibition
of eating a non-kosher bird. I've transgressed the prohibition of eating products
that derive from non-kosher animals, but it is not considered the non-kosher
animal itself. If I eat the embryo that is now forming in
this egg, then I actually have eaten a שרץ, sheretz, I've actually
eaten a rodent, not just something that came from
a, from a pro— Only if you actually eat the thing itself
do you actually get lashes is it the most severe prohibition? Okay,
so that's why the תורה Torah says the גמרא Gemara says here
you know that if it's a lizard egg so you're if it
was just an egg of a non-kosher animal you're right you'd get
a generic prohibition of eating things that come from non-kosher animals but
if the embryo has begun to form then you've actually eaten a
non-kosher you know what do you call it? reptile and therefore you
get lashes for that prohibition. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אי
הכי מאי איריא דטמאה? ei hachi mai irya detmeiah? If we're talking
about an embryo forming then who cares that it's from a non-kosher
animal? אפילו דטהורה נמי afilu detehorah nami there's a problem of an
unformed embryo even from a kosher animal דתניא detanya it was taught
in a ברייתא: braita: כל השרץ השורץ על הארץ kol hasheretz hashoraitz
al haaretz it says regarding any creepy thing that crawls on the
ground לרבות lerabot to include and we thought we were all behind
but I know the size of the next sub-verse לרבות... lerabot... לרבות
אפרוחים שלא נפתחו עיניהם. lerabot efrochim shelo niftchu eineihem.
You can't even eat chicks that have yet to open their eyes.
This is a statement in another גמרא Gemara that attributes this to
רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov that says that why
does the גמרא Gemara say the תורה Torah say you can't eat
everything that creeps on the ground? It says there are some things
that are actually kosher species but they are at a stage where
they're just where they're like creepy things like a chick before it's
opened its eyes is not really yet a chick it's not really
yet a bird you know and it's sort of like a creepy
thing and therefore that's also prohibited. And if that's true how much
more so would it be prohibited while it was still an embryo?
So who cares that this is an embryonic lizard or you know
whatever reptile? Aren't even chicken eggs before the chick has hatched and
it's developed in certain and certainly at before it's opened its eyes
and certainly at the embryonic stage aren't these also prohibited? So the
גמרא Gemara, says no מדרבנן. miderabbanan. That's only rabbinic. וקרא אסמכתא בעלמא.
vekra asmachta bealma. The verse is just a nice support but no
clearly if it's a chicken it's not non-kosher. Obviously chickens are kosher
even before they've opened their eyes and even at the embryonic stage
and therefore the problem though is with an embryo developing within an
egg if it is if it is a lizard then you're transgressing
eating a lizard or a snake. If it's a non-kosher bird you're
transgressing eating that even if it hasn't to repeat what I said
before even if it hasn't yet become an embryo you transgress for
eating something that came from a non-kosher animal but once the embryo
has begun to develop it's like you've actually eaten the non-kosher animal
itself. Okay so that is now eggs. We've determined how to look
for kosher eggs non-kosher eggs but do you need the corroborating statement
of the person who sells it or not? And we've and but
because these are not absolute סימנים you might not be able to
trust them fully you might not be able to determine whether the
birds are kosher or not based on the eggs. And now we've
also talked about the question about you know that eggs that come
from non-kosher animals are non-kosher if an embryo is developing within it
then it's actually considered to be the animal itself. And now we
are going to talk about egg spots. So let's talk about kosher
eggs about spots on your eggs. So let's take a look. Blood
spots on eggs right. So let's take a look. תנו רבנן tanu
rabbanan we taught: גיעולי
ביצים מותרות. giulei beitzim mutarot. Now what does this mean? גיעול. giul.
גיעול giul can sometimes mean like abomination it can also mean to
spit forth. So רש"י Rashi says what it means is if you
cooked non-kosher eggs together with kosher eggs and everything is in their
shell the kosher eggs remain kosher because very almost no taste goes
out from an egg when it's in its shell and cooking in
water. Hard boiled eggs in their shell and how much gets in
through the other eggshell? So רש"י Rashi says if non-kosher and kosher
eggs are all cooked in their shells together then what spits out
from the non-kosher eggs is not a problem. Nothing no taste really
comes out. We're going to see that later in the גמרא Gemara
as well.
Yeah does this mean you can get hard boiled eggs in a
restaurant? Non-kosher restaurant? Oh interesting.
In theory yes. If you're asking me a practical הלכה halakha question
I'll have to I'll have to reflect on it before giving you
a
פסק. psak. I mean there are definitely people that do that and
this comes up later in the גמרא Gemara so but I just
want to you
know let me reflect on it not in the middle of the
דף daf before giving you a פסק psak on that. Okay anyway
that's what רש"י Rashi says. תוספות Tosfos says it means that the
hen has spewed it out which means that the hen
was the hen was hit and therefore it dropped its egg before
its time. And therefore it's not a problem because this gets to
an interesting question the גמרא Gemara has. We were talking about things
that come from non-kosher animals are non-kosher but the גמרא Gemara has
another question: why isn't anything that comes from a live animal אבר
מן החי? ever min hachai? So why isn't milk אבר מן החי?
ever min hachai? Why aren't eggs אבר מן החי? ever min hachai?
They are a something that came from a living animal. So the
גמרא Gemara learns out that you know that no milk is permissible
eggs are permissible these are not אבר מן החי ever min hachai
they're also not really a limb of the animal altogether. I know
I know. So anyway but the גמרא Gemara raises that question at
one time. So you might have thought okay that's if it separates
naturally but if you hit the chicken hen and the egg drops
before its time maybe at this stage the hen the egg was
really more part of the hen and therefore it is an אבר
מן החי, Ever Min Hachay, so it's saying that it's not. So
that's the way תוספות Tosfos, learns that. Okay, now ביצים מוזרות, Beitzim
Muzarot, however,
how these sort of like, I don't know exactly how to translate
the word מוזרות, Muzarot, but it basically means a brooded egg, an
egg that was never fertilized, that was also that the hen sat
on for a long time. נפש יפה תאכלם, Nefesh Yafah Tocheilem, if
you are of a fine soul, which really means if you're not
finicky, it's a euphemism, if you're not finicky you eat it, meaning
if you are finicky, finicky people don't want to sit eat eggs
that were brooded on for a long time, they somehow are a
little less pleasant to eat. I don't know. But anyway, נמצא עליה
קורט דם, Nimtza Aleha Koret Dam, if there is a blood drop
on it, okay, then זורק את הדם ואוכל את השאר. Zorek Es
Hadam V'Ochel Es Hashar. Throw out the blood and eat the rest.
Now, why is that? So, it could be that because if these
are unfertilized eggs, a blood spot is nothing, it's not from a
fertilized—it's not from fertilization. There's actually one opinion in תוספות, Tosfos it
could also be that even if it is a fertilized egg, if
it's on a part of the egg where it doesn't sort of
spread, then it's localized and therefore it's only—only the blood is a
problem, but it doesn't impact the whole egg. Let's read another line
in the גמרא and I'll talk about the possibilities. אמר רבי ירמיה,
Amar Rabbi Yirmeyah, רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmeyah said, והוא שנמצא על קשר
שלה, V'Hu Shenimtza Al Kesher Shelah, when is that true? That's when
it is on the קשר, Kesher, which is sort of the cluster.
רש״י Rashi says they had a gorgeous picture in the ArtScroll I
saw, anyway, but it's somehow the area either at one of the
ends of the—of the—of the egg, either the pointy end or the
rounded end of the egg, and רש״י Rashi says that's where the
embryo begins to form when it's fertilized. Okay, that's when it's a
problem. אבל, Aval, he says, תני רבי דוסתאי אבוה דרבי אפטוריקי, Tani
Rabbi Dostai Avua DeRabbi Aptoriki, לא שנו אלא שנמצא על חלבון שלה,
Lo Shanu Ela Shenimtza Al Chelbon Shelah, and even this is only
if it's on the white. אבל נמצא על חלמון שלה, Aval Nimtza
Al Chelmon Shelah, if it's on the yellow, then אפילו ביצה אסורה,
Afilu Beitzah Asurah, the whole egg is forbidden.
מאי טעמא, Mai Ta'ama, what's the reason?
דשדא תיכלא בכולה. D'shada Tichla B'chulah. It has spread its spoiling throughout
it, meaning it's like the whole egg is now—the real development of
the embryo has begun and it's drawing on the whole egg and
therefore it impacts—the status affects the whole egg. Now, before we get
to where it's found, why is a blood spot a problem? I
mean, it's not the blood of a—of an actual live animal, right?
The תורה Torah only forbids the blood of a live animal. This
is just the blood—this is really just the forming of an embryo.
So תוספות Tosfos has a whole quest why blood spots are forbidden,
which is a pretty good question to ask, and he has two
answers. One is that it's completely rabbinic because if we let you
eat these blood spots, you'll come to eat the, you know, blood
from—from animals, so you know, which is really forbidden. And his other
answer is that maybe it is biblical, but it is—and it is
forbidden because, let me just see how he says it,
yeah, he says that maybe because it
is—because the chick will form from it, it is considered to be
as if it was blood that came from an actual chick. Okay,
so תוספות Tosfos is not exactly clear why it's forbidden, he seems
to be more inclined to assume that it's rabbinic, but maybe it's
as if it were real blood from a chicken and it's forbidden.
Now, because of that, there's... blood from the chicken...
well, from
a forming chicken.
It's a forming...
Is blood from a forming chicken like blood from a chicken?
Blood indicates a formation.
I understand. So when the תורה Torah forbids us to eat blood
from chickens and cows and so on, does it also forbid us
to eat blood from those things in formation? That's why תוספות Tosfos
is more inclined to say the whole thing is a rabbinic problem.
Okay, but anyway, I agree, I understand, but he's inclined to say
the whole thing is a rabbinic problem. Now, because of that, it's
only a problem at most when you're actually dealing with a forming
embryo. So if you have non-fertilized eggs and you have a blood
spot, it could be that's why the גמרא says before throw it
out, but תוספות Tosfos has another possibility of reading the גמרא, that
the whole גמרא when it's talking about blood spots was if it
were fertilized. If it's not fertilized, maybe you can even eat the
blood spot because it's not even really an embryo.
And how do you know, he says?
Well, nowadays you know, none of the eggs we are getting have
seen a rooster in their life. So let
me... I've never seen a rooster.
I understand, but we used to
go... we'd throw out that egg, but if you were cracking eggs
in a bowl, right, and you found one with a blood spot,
you throw it out?
I have. No, no... I'm asking.
But we don't get blood spots anymore. If you open...
you crack an egg and you see a blood... a blood spot,
you're not supposed to throw the egg out? I have.
So according to the real
הלכה, Halachah, according to the real הלכה, Halachah, if you've got a
blood spot on a non-fertilized egg, which is basically all of our
eggs, you can certainly just throw out the blood spot and keep
the rest, and you might be able to even eat the blood
spot, which is what תוספות says because it's not a real blood
spot. Okay? Or even if it's blood, it's not really coming from
a fertilized thing. But certainly you can just throw it out. If
it is from a fertilized egg, that's where there's these concerns about
how to read this גמרא about the white and the yellow and
where on the white and at what stage does it impact the
whole egg? And we've never bought... if you got... if you went...
I don't know the story now about these free-range, you know,
farm
farm whatever, those maybe there are roosters around and maybe you do
have to be concerned, okay? But in the factory-produced eggs where they
keep where there's no roosters anywhere, okay, there they are certainly not
fertilized and worst-case scenario just throw out the blood spot.
Okay, well when you get an organic, whatever, organic
things, that's where you're gonna... you're gonna throw...
I just threw out three eggs today.
Really? Okay. That could be different. Okay. Let's just read... okay, I
know it's 8:30. I just want to read one more sentence so
we're not super behind. אמר ליה רב גביה מבי כתיל לרב אשי.
Amar lei Rav Gaviha mi-bei Katil le-Rav Ashi. So, רב גביה Rav
Gaviha from בי כתיל bei Katil said to רב אשי: Rav Ashi:
איפכא תני תנא קמיה דאביי. Ipcha tani tana kamei d'Abaye. The actual
תנא tanna taught in front of אביי Abaye the reverse. That on
the yellow wasn't so bad, on the white you had to throw
it all out. ואביי הוא דתרצינהו ניהליה. V'Abaye hu d'tartzinhu nihaleh. And
אביי Abaye was the one who reversed it for him and said
no, no, no, on the white you just throw the egg... the
spot, on the yellow then you have to throw out the whole
egg. Okay, הכי אמר חזקיה. Hachi amar Chizkiyah. Now, וניהלי הכי. v'nihali
hachi.
So, fine. Sends it that way. One more line. אמר חזקיה: Amar
Chizkiyah: מניין לביצת טמאה שהיא אסורה? Minayin l'beitzat temei'ah she-hi asurah? How
do I know that eggs of non-kosher birds are forbidden? This idea
of derivative from non-kosher animals. מן התורה? Min ha-Torah? שנאמר: She-ne'emar: ואת
בת היענה. V'et bat ha-ya'anah.
One of the forbidden birds is the ostrich, which is called the
בת היענה. bat ha-ya'anah. וכי בת יש לו ליענה? Vechi bat yesh
lo l'ya'anah? Do ostriches have daughters? Meaning, it's considered that you call
something a daughter if it was a live birth. But if it's
coming through an egg, you wouldn't call something a daughter. So, it's
not... there can't have real daughters. אלא איזו היא? Ela eizo hi?
What is considered the child of this animal? זו ביצה טמאה. Zu
beitzah temei'ah. It means the egg. So, the תורה Torah forbids the
בת היענה, bat ha-ya'anah, which we are assuming to mean the thing
given birth to by the יענה, ya'anah, the eggs are forbidden as
well. ודילמא היינו שמה? V'dilma haynu shemah? So, the גמרא says maybe
that's just what it's called! Maybe the name of an ostrich is
בת היענה. bat ha-ya'anah. No. לא סלקא דעתך. Lo salka d'atach.
That doesn't make sense. דכתיב: De-chtiv: בת עמי לאכזר כיענים במדבר. Bat
ami l'achzar k'ye'enim ba-midbar. The daughter of my people have become cruel
like ostriches in the wilderness. And there it doesn't say בת, bat,
it just says יענים. ye'enim. So, you see בת bat is an
extra word, and therefore it means the egg. The גמרא
says: ולא? V'lo? והא כתיב: Ve-ha chtiv: אעשה מספד כתנים
ואבל כבנות יענה.
E'eseh misped k'tanim v'eivel ki-vnot
ya'anah.
We'll do a mourning like the jackals and a mourning like the
בנות יענה. vnot ya'anah. So, you see בנות יענה vnot ya'anah are
the... are is the name of the animal. So, the גמרא says:
No. כי ענה זו שמתאבלת על בניה. Ki yanah zo she-mitabelet al
baneha. It means the way an ostrich would mourn for her children.
But again, the word בנות vnot means the children. והא כתיב: Ve-ha
chtiv: ושכנו שם בנות יענה. V'shachnu sham vnot ya'anah.
They'll dwell there the בנות יענה. vnot ya'anah. So, you see it's
the name of the ostrich. So, the גמרא says: No. כי ענה
זו ששוכנת עם בניה. Ki yanah zo she-shochenet im baneha. Like an
ostrich that dwells with her children. So, we will end here. We
will find out tomorrow whether the actual name of the ostrich is
a בת יענה bat ya'anah or whether בת יענה bat ya'anah refers
to the eggs and from there is where we learn out that
the eggs of non-kosher birds are also not kosher.